Pooja Saurabh Satose, PhD (Biotechnology-Life Science)

301, Kamalchaya Apartment, Yashodhan Nagar Thane - (W), Thane - 400 606 Maharashtra, India 🗒 +91-9769722046



Professional summary

pchavan19@gmail.com

A young dynamic professional with 4 years of research and two year of teaching expertise as well as a basic understanding of general biological sciences principles. Looking forward to apply my knowledge and experience in a new environment.

Skills

Strong critical and analytical skills, Passion for connecting students to learning, Voracious appetite for increasing knowledge

Experience

Karmaveer Bhaurao Patil College, Vashi — Assistant Professor

JAN 2020 - OCT, 2021

- Teaching graduate students of Biotechnology
- Subjects taught: Molecular biology, Industrial microbiology & Bioinformatics, Animal physiology, Skill based subject - Food technology
- Prepared syllabus, reading materials, online tests and quizzes

B. N. Bandodkar College of Science, Thane - Assistant Professor

JUL 2017 - APR 2018

- Teaching graduate students of Biotechnology & Microbiology
- Subjects taught: Genetics, Industrial microbiology, Biophysics
- Assisted final year students for skilled based projects

Bhabha Atomic Research Centre, Kalpakkam — Research Fellow

JUN 2012 - MAR 2017

- Research on ecotoxicological effects of power plant effluents on marine model organisms
 Diatoms & Invertebrate.
- Analysis of water characteristics & phytoplankton cell count under influence of thermal power plant

Experience Instrument & Techniques

Gel electrophoresis (Native and SDS-PAGE) and activity staining of the gels, qRT-PCR, Gene expression studies, Comet assay, DNA diffusion assay, Bright-field and Epi-fluorescence microscopy, UV Spectrophotometer, HPLC, GC, Sonicator, Multimode reader, Respirometer, FlowCAM, Algal culture & Identification, Environmental monitoring, Statistical Data analysis in dedicated statistical softwares (Microsoft Excel, Origin, GarphPad Prism, PAST)

Education

PhD (As per UGC Regulation 2009), Biotechnology – Life Science (2019)

Madras University, Chennai

MSc, Biotechnology (2011)

65.20%, Birla College, Mumbai University

BSc, Biotechnology (2009)

74.00%, K.J. Somaiya College of Science & Commerce, Mumbai University

H.S.C. (2006)

80.50%, K.J. Somaiya College of Science & Commerce, Maharashtra State Board

S.S.C. (2004)

86.87%, Sharada Vidyalaya, Maharashtra State Board

Publications

- Pooja Chavan, Rajesh Kumar, Ramalingam Kirubagaran, Vayalam P. Venugopalan, 2016. Chlorination induced genotoxicity in the green mussels *Perna viridis*: assessment by single cell gel electrophoresis (comet) assay. Ecotoxicology and Environmental Safety 130; 295–302. DOI 10.1016/j.ecoenv.2016.04.034
- 2. **Pooja Chavan**, Rajesh Kumar, Ramalingam Kirubagaran, Vayalam P. Venugopalan, 2017. Comparative toxicological effects of two antifouling biocides on the marine diatom *Chaetoceros lorenzianus*: damage and post-exposure recovery. Ecotoxicology and Environmental Safety, 144; 97-106. DOI 10.1016/j.ecoenv.2017.06.001
- 3. **Pooja Chavan**, Rajesh Kumar, Hiren Joshi, Ramalingam Kirubagaran, Vayalam P. Venugopalan, 2018. A multimarker study on the effects of chlorine in benthic organisms using *Perna viridis* as candidate species. Environmental Science and Pollution Research, 25(21), 20407-20418. DOI 10.1007/s11356-017-9607
- 4. **Pooja Chavan**, Rajesh Kumar, Ramalingam Kirubagaran, Vayalam P. Venugopalan. Bromoform toxicity to marine microalgae: studies using the diatom *Chaetoceros lorenzianus* as a model organism. [Manuscript under review]
- 5. **Pooja Chavan**, Rajesh Kumar, Ramalingam Kirubagaran, Vayalam P. Venugopalan. Physiological and biochemical changes in *Chaetoceros lorenzianus* on exposure to antifouling biocides, chlorine and chlorine dioxide. [*Manuscript under review*]
- 6. **PhD thesis Title**: Biomarker based ecotoxicological studies on marine biota subjected to antifouling biocides: observations from field and laboratory.

Awards

- 1. First prize for a poster presented at the International Conference on Advanced Technologies for Management of Ballast Water and Biofouling (MABB 2014).
- 2. Second prize for poster in International Conference on Water: From Pollution to Purification (ICW-2016).

Conferences and Workshop

1. National Conference on Genomics, Proteomics & System Biology held in J. N. Tata Auditorium, IISC Campus, Bangalore on 1-3 October, 2008.

- 2. International Conference on Advanced Technologies for Management of Ballast Water and Biofouling (MABB 2014), Jointly organised by NIOT and BARC, Govt.of India on 4-7 March, 2014, NIOT, Chennai, India.
- 3. Participated in Theme Meeting on Cooling Water Treatment for Biofouling Control, organised by Biofouling and Biofilm Processes Section (Water and Steam Chemistry Division), DAE-COSWAC, 23 rd 24 th April, 2015, Kalpakkam, India.
- 4. Participated in the Science Academies Lecture workshop on "Advances in microalgal research and its relevance to climate change" organised by Centre for Climate Change Studies at Sathyabama University, Chennai, India during 21st 22nd July, 2016.
- 5. International Conference on Water: From Pollution to Purification (ICW-2016) organized by Mahatma Gandhi University, Kerala, India on 13-15 December, 2016.

Training

- 1. Completed successfully "Certificate Course in Laboratory Techniques (Three Months)" conducted by K. J. Somaiya College of Science & Commerce, Vidyavihar, Mumbai in 2007.
- 2. Three months project training as a part of MSc Dissertation on 'Method optimization for analysis of biotransformed steroid using thin layer chromatography and high-performance liquid chromatography' in Ipca Pharmaceuticals Ltd., Kandiwali.
- 3. Completed online Short -Term Bioinformatics Training from Arraygen Technologies Pvt Ltd. Pune in January, 2020
- 4. Completed online Next Generation Sequencing (NGS) certificate course on Biotecnika in April, 2020.
- 5. Completed three days online training on NGS data analysis from RASA Life Science Informatics from 25th -27th February, 2021.
- 6. Pursuing one-month online training on "Plant Genomics & Bioinformatics" from Decode Life Bioinformatics Training Institute from 19th March 17th April, 2022.

Faculty Development Program (FDP):

- 1. Three days National level FDP on 'online college management & online content creation tools' organized by Lala Lajpat Rai College of Commerce & Economics, University of Mumbai and North Storm Academy on 30th April, 1st & 2nd May, 2020.
- 2. National level Bootcamp for Teachers organised by North Storm Academy on $15^{\rm th}$ to $17^{\rm th}$ May, 2020.
- 3. Three-day National level workshops on 'Blended Learning Approaches in Biosciences' organized by Microbiology Society of India on 28th June to 30th June, 2020.
- 4. Participated in National online 'Faculty Development Programme on Virtual Labs: Education 4.0' organized by Virtual Labs Nodal Centre MIT Art, Design & Technology University, Rajbaug, Pune in association with V-Labs, NMEICT-MHRD, SOLVE-NITK and Center of System Design on Thursday July 23, 2020.
- 5. Participated in offline Science Academies Refresher course in "Recent Trends in Molecular Biology: Concepts & Practice" in collaboration with Department of Biotechnology, Dr. B R Ambedkar University, Srikakulum from 2nd 15th March, 2021.

References

1. Dr. Vayalam P. Venugopalan

Associate Director, Bioscience group (Retired) Head, Nuclear Agriculture and Biotechnology Division (NABTD) Bhabha Atomic Research Centre (BARC) Trombay, Mumbai 400 085, Maharashtra, India

Mob: +91 9442294906 Email: vpvenu@gmail.com

2. Dr. Rajesh Kumar

Scientific Officer F Planning and Coordination Division (P&CD), Bhabha Atomic Research Centre (BARC), Trombay, Mumbai 40085

Tel: +91 22 25597603 Mob: +91 9443067615

E-mail: <u>rkausis@barc.gov.in</u>; <u>rajesh.kausis@gmail.com</u>

Personal details

Spouse name: Saurabh Keshav Satose

Birth date: 19th October, 1988

Marital status: Married

Languages known: English, Hindi, Marathi

Hobbies: Reading novels, cycling, travelling, trekking, gardening

Declaration

I, Pooja Chavan-Satose, hereby declare that the information contained herein is true and correct to the best of my knowledge and belief.